Finding Aid for the Norman Douglas Papers LSC.0111
UCLA Library Special Collections
Norman Douglas papers
1879-1952
UCLA Library Special Collections
Douglas, Norman
LSC.0111
8.5 Linear Feet (17 boxes)
George Norman Douglas (1868-1952) was a British author, scientist, diplomat, and editor. The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, corrected proofs, and notebooks related to Douglas' early scientific interests and literary career.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Leon Gelber, 1948.
Robin Douglas, purchase, 1953 and 1955.
Gift of Robin Douglas, 1954-56.
Ben Abramson, purchase, 1955.
Bertram Rota, purchase, 1958.
Beauchamp Bookshop, purchase, 1963.
Doris Harris, purchase, 1969 and 1985.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID:9912178623606533
We are committed to providing ethical, inclusive, and anti-racist description of the materials we steward, and to remediating existing description of our materials that contains language that may be offensive or cause harm. We invite you to submit feedback about how our collections are described, and how they could be described more accurately, by filling out the form located on our website: Report Potentially Offensive Description in Library Special Collections.
Biography
George Norman Douglas was born December 8, 1868 in Falkenhorst, Thuringen, Austria; recognized as British author, scientist, diplomat, and editor; began writing career composing zoological texts while in foreign service; published first work of fiction, Unprofessional tales (1901), under pseudonym Normyx; contributor and assistant editor, English review; best known as novelist and travel writer; greatest American success was with novel, South wind (1917); other novels and publications include Siren land (1911), Old Calabria (1928), Looking back (1933), Late harvest (1946); died on the island of Capri, 1952.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, corrected proofs, and notebooks related to Douglas' early scientific interests and literary career. The bulk of the papers cover his literary career, and correspondents include: Martha Gordon Croutch, Richard Curle, Robin Douglas, Leon Gelber, Frank Harris, William Henry Hudson, Edward Hutton, Frieda Lawrence, Walter Lowenfels, Giuseppe Oriolo, Grant Richards, Martin Secker, Montague Sumners, Reginald Turner, and others. Material related to Douglas's scientific interests (1879-1905) includes correspondence with Georg Albert Boulenger, Albert Girtanner, James Edmund Harting, Franz von Leydig, Hugh Alexander MacPherson, and Margherita Traube-Mengarini.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence (Boxes 1-5).
Manuscripts, notebooks, proofs, clippings, photographs, typescripts, and ephemera (Boxes 6-8, 17).
Limited editions of some of Douglas's works (Box 9).
Books from Douglas' library (Boxes 10-17).
Scientists -- Archives.; Authors, English -- Archives.; Douglas, Norman, 1868-1952--Archives.
- Correspondence
  General note
  The guide should be consulted for greater details, keeping in mind that the grouping has been greatly altered, as indexed here:
  - Index of Correspondents: (In individual folders) (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Boulenger, Georg Albert, 1858-. 10 items (to N. Douglas).
    Crotch, Martha Gordon, Auntie 70 items.
    Curle, Richard, 1883-. 46 items (from N. Douglas).
    Dibben, W.H., 23 items (from N. Douglas).
    Gelber, Leon 18 items (from N. Douglas).
    Girtanner, Albert, 1839-1907. 15 items (to and from N. Douglas).
    Harris, Frank, Letters...1939. 4 items (from N. Douglas).
    Harting, James Edmund, 1841-1928. (to and from N. Douglas) 17 items.
    Honn, Alice E. 2 folders, 72 items (from N. Douglas).
    Hudson, William Henry, 1841-1922. 4 items (to N. Douglas).
  - Index of Correspondents (Continued) (Box 2)
    Lownfels, Walter, 1897-. 53 items (from N. Douglas).
    Leydig, Franz, 1821-1908. 26 items (to and from N. Douglas).
    Mac Pherson, Hugh Alexander, 1858-1901. 25 items (to and from N. Douglas).
    Searle, W. Townley 25 items (from N. Douglas).
    Straus, Ralph, 1882-1950. 4 folders, 187 items (from N. Douglas).
    Terzian (photocopies) 21 items (from N. Douglas).
    Turner, Reginald, d. 1939. 31 items (from N. Douglas).
  - General Correspondence. Letters from Norman Douglas to various persons, 1916-1936.; 1 folder, 26 items. (Box 2)
    Dear Bunny
    Flight, F.L.
    Gilbertson, I.S.
    Gye, Ernest Frederick, 1879-.
    Ives, George Burnham, 1856-1930 [2].
    Lane, John, 1854-1925.
    W. Jackson [London Bookseller].
    Lawrence, Frieda (von Richthofen), 1879-.
    Nicolson, Hon. Harold George, 1886-. -[form ORIOLI].
    Parsons, Ian [letters drafted by N.D. for Orioli] [2].
    Sabatini, Rafael, 1875-.
    Savage, Derek [?] [probably Henry Savage] [2].
    Secker, Martin [4].
    Richards, Grant, 1872-. [3].
    Venn, M. [5].
    [Dear Sir, February 12, 1925].
    [Dear Bill, January 6, 1945].
  - Letters to Norman Douglas from various persons, 1914-1950.; 1 folder, 14 items. (Box 2)
    Adelswärd-Fersen, Jacques d', baron.
    Banca Nazionale, Firenze.
    Cook's, Rome (Sr. Gugliehmi).
    Newton, Eric, 1893-.
    Petrina, Carlotta, 1901-. (1 letter to N. Douglas, 1930; 2 letters to George Macy re illustrations for South Wind, 1931).
    Sigerist, Henry Ernst, 1891-.
    Summers, Montague, 1880-.
    Von Hagen, Victor Wolfgang, 1908-.
  - Scientific correspondence, 1889-1901.; 20 items. (Box 2)
    Barington, E.C.
    Barrington.
    Beaman, S.G. Hulme.
    Carus, J. Victor, 1823-1903.
    Günther, Albert Carl Ludwig, 1830-1914.
    Mackie, Henry Brown.
    [Mitchell].
    Service, Robert William, 1876-.
    Sim, G.
    Smith, Edgar Albert, 1874-.
    Traube-Mengarini, Margherita.
    Wallace, Alfred Russell, 1823-1913.
    Waterhouse, Charles Owen, 1843-1917.
  - Correspondence of Edward Hutton, 1875- with Norman Douglas, 1918-1950, as well as with various others of their mutual acquaintance, 1918-1942.; 9 folders, 486 items. (Box 2, Box 3)
    [Hutton to Douglas correspondence, 1919-1950].
    Cosson, de, baron. 11 items.
    Douglas, Archie 11 items (To E. Hutton).
    Orioli, Giuseppe, 1884-1942. 7 items (To E. Hutton).
    Turner, Reginald, d. 1938. 39 items (2 folders) (To E. Hutton).
  - Norman Douglas, 1868-1952. Letters to Guiseppe Orioli, 1884-1942. v.p., 1922-1939.; 12 folders, 455 items. (Box 4)
  - Norman Douglas, 1868-1952. Letters to Giuseppe Orioli; Scraps, etc., 1 folders, 58 items. (Box 5)
  - Letters from Giuseppe Orioli to Dr. Crummer, 1924-1931.; 8 items. (Box 5)
  - Drafts of letters composed by Douglas for Orioli's use., 19 items. (Box 5)
  - Letters to Orioli from various persons, re Norman Douglas., 12 items. (Box 5)
  - Norman Douglas, 1868-1952. Letters to Robin Douglas, 1904-. v.p., 2 folders in a manila envelope., 1921-1939.; 41 items. (Box 5)
  - Norman Douglas, 1868-1952. Letters to Robin Douglas. Portugal & England, 1941-1944.; 9 items. (Box 5)
  - Letters to Robin Douglas re Norman Douglas, from various persons., 6 items. (Box 5)
- Manuscripts, Ephemera, and Books
  For detailed descriptions of the manuscripts, ephemera, and books contained in Boxes 6-9, the earlier guide should be consulted. This an index to the revised grouping. Boxes 1-5 contain the correspondence: grouping also revised.
  Revised by E. Vécsey, Febraury 8, 1962.
  - Autobiographical materials: extracts from notebooks, letters., n.d.; 17 items. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, ephemera re emigration of Norman Douglas to the United States. v.p., 1941.; 15 items. (Box 6)
  - [De natura hominis] n.p., n.d.; Holograph manuscript in German. 21 leaves. (Box 6)
  - Disiecta membra: materials for a description of Capri., Photostats. 137 leaves. (Box 6)
    - Index [to the Capri monographs], 1915 (Box 18)
      Scope and Content
      Proof copy for the edition of 100 copies issued 1913. Heavily annotated throughout in the author's hand and with his initials on page 333. This index, the last pamphlet of the Capri series, was issued for private distribution. Original red wrappers inscirbed "Press N.D." In a grey buckram folding case, red morocco label, gilt.
      Provenance/Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Majl Ewing, undated.
  - Douglas Calendar - index, correspondence with agents., 1927.; 5 items. (Box 6)
  - Ephemera - clippings, etc., 6 items. (Box 6)
  - List of important people in case of death. 1952(?)., 1 leaf. (Box 6)
  - Material (on coloration of bird-eggs), 1887.; Holograph. 18 leaves. (Box 6)
  - Notebooks, Germany and England, (On natural science)., 1872-1886; Holograph. 7 items. (Box 6)
  - A plea for the German professor. n.p., during World War I., Typescript. 3 leaves. (Box 6)
  - Scientific ephemera: maps, notes, clippings, drawings., 17 items. (Box 6)
  - Theophilus, or They went. Author's explantion., n.d.; Typescript. 8 leaves. (Box 6)
  - Tribulations of a patriot. n.p., (during World War I) clipped article., 5 leaves. (Box 6)
  - Portraits, photographs of Norman, Robin Douglas, etc., 22 items. (Box 6)
  - In the beginning (Florence, 1927) 4 signatures, unbound. (Box 7)
  - Last of the Medici (introduction), 1930.; Holograph. 16 leaves. (Box 7)
  - Late harvest. London, 1946.; Typescript. Blue wrappers. 224pp. (Box 7)
  - Table showing the results of an examination., [Photostat] 1 leaf. (Box 7)
  - Theophilus. (Dramatization) n.p., n.d.; Typescript. bound folio. 99pp. (Box 7)
  - Venus in the kitchen by Pilaff Bey. n.p., n.d.; Typescript (carbon) orange boards. 217pp. (Box 7)
  - Woolf, Cecil. [Bio-bibliography of Norman Douglas, n.p., 1954.; Typescript. Chapter 1. 15 leaves. (Box 7)
  - An almanac, version corrected for press. Portugal, 1941.; Typescript with holograph introduction. Red slip-case. (Box 7)
  - Alone. (Earlier manuscript). n.p., n.d.; Holograph, with markings. Bound folio. 325pp. (Box 8)
  - Alone. Index to manuscript. Florence, Holograph, typescript. In notebook. 50 leaves. (Box 8)
  - Fountains in the sand, First and quite different version., Typescript. Bound folio. 229pp. (Box 8)
  - The familiar spirit. n.p., 1896.; Holograph, typescript. Unpublished. Bound folio. 325 pages. (Box 8)
  - Books - privately printed, limited editions, etc., 9 books. (Box 9)
    A fragment (in The Fist Edition and Book Colledtor)/
    Late harvest. London, 1946. Sepia cloth.
    On the Darwinian hypothesis of sexual selection (pam).
    Paneros. Florence, 1930. Full gilt cloth, embossed.
    Some Limericks. n.p., 1928. Yellow cloth (no.47).
    Some Limericks. n.p., 1928. Beige cloth.
    South Wind. London, Martin Secker, 1935.
    Together. London, Chapman & Hall, 1923. ½ leather.
    Venus in the kitchen. Heinemann Limited Proof copy.
    FOR ADDITIONAL MANUSCRIPT MATERIAL, SEE BOX 17.
  - South Wind, 1945 (Box 18)
    Proof-sheets for the 1945 Secker edition, marked with revisions by Douglas' friend, William King.
  - The Life of the Venerable Suor Serafina Di Dio: with notes bibiographical and historical, 1907 (Box 18)
    Presentation copy to S. E. Brooks, signed by the author and with corrections in his hand. Limited edition of 100 copies.
- Group IV Books from the Library of Norman Douglas
  Some of the books are plated with the armorial Douglas bookplate, some of them have N. Douglas' early signature on fly-leaf (G.N. Douglas), later purchases bear the rubber-stamp book-mark N.D.
  - 1: Anthologia graeca, with English translations by W.R. Paton. London, Heinemann, 1917 (Loeb Classical Library) vol.3 (of 5). (Box 15)
  - 2: Anthologia graeca, epigrammatum anthologia palatina cum planudeis et appendice nova.... Fred. Dübner. Graece et Latine. Paris, Firmin-Didot, 3 vol. (Box 15)
  - 3: Athenaeus: the Deipnosophists, with English translation by Charles Burton Gulock. London, Heinemann, (Loeb Classical Library. vol.5 (of 7)., 1933 (Box 15)
  - 4: Bedriaga, J von. Beiträge zur Kenntnis der Lacertiden Familie. Frankfurt, 1886. (Box 15)
  - Separat Abdruck der Abhandlungen der Senckenberg. naturforschenden Gesellschaft, vol.14, s.17. (Box 15)
    With full length letter by N.D. on fly leaf.
  - 5: Bergse, Vilhelm, 1835-1911. Italienische Novellen. Aus dem Daenischen von Wilhelm Lange. Leipzig, Reclam, (A few annotations in Douglas' hand). (Box 15)
  - 6: British Ornithologists' Union. A list of British birds compiled by a committee of the British Ornithologists' Union. London, Van Voorst, 1883. (Box 16)
  - 7: Brehm, Alfred Edmund, 1829-1884. Brehms Tierleben. 2. Ausg. Leipzig, Bibliographisches Institut, vol.7 only: 3. Ahtheilung: Kriechtiere., 1883. (Box 16)
  - 8: Burnaby, Frederick Gustoavus, 1842-1885 Ride to Khiva: travels and adventures in Central Asia. 10th ed. London, Cassell Petter & Galpin, 1877. (Box 16)
  - 9: Calderon, George, 1868-1915. Tahiti by Tihoti (George Calderon). London, Grant Richards, 1921. (Box 16)
  - 10: Censored Mother Goose Rhymes. New York, Knopf, 1930. (Box 16)
  - 11: Caracciolo, Enrichetta, 1821-1901. Memoirs of... Princess of Forino, ex-Benedictine Nun. 3rd ed. London, Bentley, 1865. (Box 16)
  - 12: Du Chaillu, Paul Belloni, 1831-1903. Explorations and adventures in equatorial Africa, London, Murray, 1861. (Box 16)
  - 13: Doelter y Cisterich, Cornelius August, 1850-1930. Die Vulkangruppe der pontinischen Inseln. (Mathematisch -Naturwissenschafltiche Classe, April 15, 1875. (Box 10)
  - 14: Durr, Julius. Reisen des Kaisers Hadrian. Abh. des Archäologischen-epigraphischen Seminars d. Univ. Wien. Heft II. Wien, 1881. (Box 16)
  - 15: Fatio, Victor, 1838-1906. Faune des vertébrés de la Suisse. Genéve, H. Georg, vol.3 (of 5): Histoire naturelle des reptiles et des batraciens., 1872. (Box 16)
  - 16: Goldsmith, Oliver, 1728-1774. Poetical works... Cooke's edition. London, Cooke, (ca. 1795). (Box 16)
  - 17: Gubernatis, Angelo de, Conte, 1840-1913. Zoological mythology, or the legends of animals, London, Trübner, vol.2 only., 1872. (Box 16)
  - 18: Haeckel, Ernst Heinrich Philipp August: 1834-1919. A visit to Ceylon, Translated by Clara Bell. London, Kegan Paul, Trench & Company, 1883. (Box 16)
  - 19: Harris, Frank: 1855-1931. My life. Privately printed, vol.2-3 (of 4 vol. set)., 1925. (Box 16)
  - 20: Harris, Frank: 1855-1931. Oscar Wilde, his life and confessions. New York, by the author, vol.2 only., 1916. (Box 11)
  - 21: Heer, Oswald: 1809-1883. Die Urwelt der Schweiz. Zürich, F. Schulthess, 1865. (Box 11)
  - 22: Hehn, Victor: 1813-1890. Kulturpflanzen und Hausthiere in ihren Ubergang aus Asien nach Griechenland... 7. Aufl. Berlin, Bornträger, 1902. (Box 11)
  - 23: Herodotus: with English translation by A.D. Godley. 4 vol. London, Heinemann, (Loeb Classical Library) vol.1 only, containing books 1 & 2., 1926. (Box 11)
  - 24: Hudson, William Henry: 1841-1922. Naturalist in La Plata. London, Chapman & Hall, 1892. (Box 11)
  - 25: Hufeland, Christian Wilhelm: 1762-1836. Art of prolonging life ed. by Erasmus Wilson. London, J. Churchill, 1853. (Box 11)
  - 26: Institoris Henricis: d. ca. 1500. Malleus Maleficarum, translated by the Reverend Montague Summers. London, John Rodker, 1929. Limited edition of 1275 copies of which this is no.1090. Signed by M. Summers. (Box 11)
  - 27: Livingstone, David: 1813-1873. Missionary travels and researches in South Africa; including a sketch of a 16 years residence in the interior of Africa. London, Murray, 1857. (Box 12)
  - 28: Ludwig, Hubert: 1852-1913. Wirbelthiere Deutschlands in übersichtlicher Darstellung. Illus. Hannover, Hahn, 1884. (Box 11)
  - 29: Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix: 1809-1847. Reisebriefe aus den Jahren 1830 bis 1832. 2. Aufl. Leipzig, Mendelsohn, 1862. (Box 11)
  - 30: Milton, John: 1608-1674. Comus, being the Bridgewater manuscript with notes and a short family memoir by Lady Alix Egerton. London, Dent, Limited edition., 1910. (Box 11)
  - 31: Ovidius Naso, Publius. Eton selections from Ovid and Tibullus... adjecit Gulielmus Gifford Cookesley. Eton, 1879. (Box 11)
  - 32: Pereira, Adolf von: Im Reiche des Aeolus. Ein Bordleben von hundert Stunden an den Liparischen Inseln. Wien, A. Hartleben, 1883. (Box 11)
  - 33: Prodgers, Cecil Herbert: Adventures in Peru. London, John Lane, 1924. (Box 11)
  - 34: Shelley, Percy Bysshe: 1792-1822. Essays, letters from abroad, translations and fragments, London, Moxon 1852., 2 vol. in 1. (Box 11)
  - 35: [Smith, James: 1775-1839] Rejected addresses... [London, W. Pople] (Box 11)
  - 36: Spratt, Thomás Abel Brimage: 1811-1888. Travels in Lycia, Milyas and the Cibyratis in company with the late Rev. E.T. Daniell.... London, John Van Voorst, 1847.; 2 vol. (Box 11)
  - 37: Unger, Franz Joseph Andreas Nicolas: 1800-1870. Die versunkene Insel Atlantis. -Die physiologischen Bedeutung der Pflanzenkultur. 2 Vorträge. Wien, Braumäller, 1860. (Box 13)
  - 38: Vonbun, Franz Joseph: 1824-1870. ed. Die Sagen Vorarlbergs. Innsbruck, Wagner, 1858. (Box 13)
  - 39: Von Hagen, Victor Wolfgang: 1908-. Ecuador and the Galapagos Islands. Norman, University of Oklahoma Press, Author's dedication to N. Douglas on fly-leaf., 1949. (Box 13)
  - 40: Wallace, Alfred Russell: 1823-1913. Tropical nature and other essays. London, MacMillan, 1878. (Box 13)
  - 41: Zimmermann, Johannes Georg: ritter von, 1728-1795. Vom Nationalstolse... 4. verbesserte Auflage, Frankfurt & Leipzig, 1780. (Box 13)
  - 42: Italian textbook: play. Title-page missing, fly-leaf: G.N. Douglas,, Karlsruge., December 1886 (Box 13)
  - 43: Gätke, Heinrich: 1814-1897. Die Vogelwarte Helgoland. Hrsg. von Rudolf Blasius. Braunschweig, J.H. Meyer, 1891. (Box 13)
  - 45: Imhoof-Blumer, Friedrich: 1838-1920. Tier- und Pflanzenbilder auf Münsun und Gemmen des klassischen Altertums. Leipzig, Teubner, 1889. (Box 13)
    Cataloged in Rare Book Cataloge
  - 46: Sitizano, Giuseppe Taccone, marchese di. De tribus Basilidianis gemmis Iosephi Marchionis Tacconii... Neapoli, Ex typographeo Angeli Trani, 1824. (Box 13)
  - 47: Abel, Jakob Friedrich: 1751-1829. Philosophische Untersuchunger über die Verbindung der Menschen mit höhern Geistern. Stutgart, Mezler, 1791. (Box 13)
  - 48: Hufeland, Christoph Wilhelm: 1762-1836. Guter Rath an M¨tter Uber die wichtigsten Punkte der physischen Erziehung der Kinder... Basel, Rottmann (Box 13)
  - 49: Giraldi, Lilio Gregorio: 1479-1552. De sepulchris & uario sepeliendi ritu libellus... Basileae, 1539. (Box 13)
  - 50: Adelsward-Fersen, Jacques, baron. Une jeunesse. Le Baiser de Narcisse. Paris, Messein, 1907. (Box 13)
    Cataloged in the Rare Book Catalog.
  - 51: _____ Le danseur aux caresses. Paris, Messein, 1906. (Box 11)
  - 52: _____ Et le feu s'éteignit sur la mer [par] Fersen. [3.éd.] Paris, Messein, 1909. (Box 11)
  - 53: Douglas, Norman. Siren land... new and revised edition. London: Martin Secker With copious manuscript notes by the author., [1923]. (Box 11)
  - 54: Douglas, Norman. Some comments on my books. In: Life and letters today. vol.39 no.76. Author's own copy with manuscript notes & corrections., December 1943. (Box 11)
  - 55: Douglas, Norman. Some comments on my books. In: Life and letters today. vol.40 no. 77. Author's own copy with manuscript notes & corrections., January 1944. (Box 11)
  - 56: Douglas, Norman. Experiments. London, Chapman and Hall, Limited, 1925. (Box 12)
    Presentation copy to Willy with notes in the author's hand, and in the hand of William King.
  - 57: Douglas, Norman. Together. London, Chapman & Hall, Limited, Notes by the author's friend William King., 1923. (Box 12)
  - 58: Douglas, Norman. Together. London, Chapman & Hall, Limited, 248pp. Presentation to Archie Douglas (the author's son) from the author, With some corrections in the author's hand., 1923. Sept. 1923. (Box 13)
  - 59: Defoe, Daniel [?]. The pleasant and surprising adventures of Robert Drury... London, Hunt and Clarke, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1826. (Box 12)
  - 60: Scott, Sir Walter. Letters on demonology and witchcraft... London, John Murray, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1830. (Box 14)
  - 61: Forbes, James David. Occasional papers on the theory of glaciers... Edinburgh, Adam and Charles Black, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1859. (Box 14)
  - 62: Mansur, Abdullah, pseudonym [Bury, George Wyman]. The land of Uz. London, Macmillan, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1911. (Box 14)
  - 63: Burton, Richard F. A mission to Gelele, king of Dahome... London, Tylston and Edwards, 2 vol. Gift of Robin Douglas., 1893. (Box 14)
  - 64: Graham, Robert Bontine Cunninghame. Mogreb-El-Acksa... New York, Viking, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1930. (Box 14)
  - 65: Cesnola, Luigi Palma di. Cyprus: its ancient cities, tombs, and temples.... New York, Hraper & Brothers, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1878. (Box 14)
  - 66: Whymper, Edward, Travels amongst the Great Andes of the equator... New York, Scribner's, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1892. (Box 14)
  - 67: Vambery, Arminius. Travels in Central Asia... London, John Murray, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1864. (Box 14)
  - 68: Burton, Richard Francis. The Nile basin... London, Tinsley Brothers, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1864. (Box 17)
  - 69: Frazer, James George. Adonis Attis Osiris: Studies in the history of Oriental religion. Second edition... London, Macmillan, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1907. (Box 17)
  - 70: Palgrave, William Gifford. Narrative of a year's journey through central and eastern Arabia (1862-63)... in two volumes. Third edition. London and Cambridge, Macmillan, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1866. (Box 17)
  - 71: Lear, Edward. Journals of a landscape painter in southern Calabria, etc. [London] Richard Bentley, Gift of Robin Douglas., 1852. (Box 17)
  - Douglas, Norman. Looking back. New York, Harcourt, Brace & Company, 1 p.l., 135 leaves. Galley proofs, uncorrected. 15 illustrations are listed in the galleys, but only 8 were published., 1933. (Box 17)
  - ___ Together. n.p., 102 pages. Holograph manuscript (incomplete) with copious corrections and additions. This is apparently the first draft. pp.103-178 missing (sections titled Valduna, Old Anna, and Schlins.) With this: Notes used for writing Together, pp.179-192., 1923.; Holograph. (Box 17)